Five years ago, I experienced a bit
قبل خمس سنوات، شهدت تجربة
of what it must have been like to be Alice in Wonderland.
مماثلة لتجربة أليس في بلاد العجائب.
Penn State asked me, a communications teacher,
طلبت مني جامعة ولاية بن، كمحاضرة اتصال،
to teach a communications class for engineering students.
أن أدرّس فصول اتصال لطلاب الهندسة.
And I was scared. (Laughter)
وقد كنت مذعورة. (ضحك)
Really scared. Scared of these students with their big brains
مذعورة حقاً. مذعورة من أولئك الطلاب ذوي الأدمغة الكبيرة
and their big books and their big, unfamiliar words.
وكتبهم الكبيرة وكلماتهم الكبيرة غير المألوفة.
But as these conversations unfolded,
لكن بينما تكشّفت هذه النقاشات،
I experienced what Alice must have when she went down
شهدت ما مرّت به أليس حينما كانت في بلاد العجائب
that rabbit hole and saw that door to a whole new world.
عبر حفرة الأرنب ورأت باباً لعالم جديد.
That's just how I felt as I had those conversations
هكذا شعرت عندما خضت هذه النقاشات
with the students. I was amazed at the ideas
مع الطلاب. لقد ذُهلت بالأفكار
that they had, and I wanted others to experience this wonderland as well.
التي لديهم، وأردت للبقية أن يستمتعوا ببلاد العجائب أيضا.
And I believe the key to opening that door
وأعتقد أن مفتاح ذلك الباب
is great communication.
هو التواصل الفعّال.
We desperately need great communication from our
نحن بحاجة ملحّة لتواصل فعّال من
scientists and engineers in order to change the world.
علمائنا ومهندسينا من أجل تغيير العالم.
Our scientists and engineers are the ones
علماؤنا ومهندسونا هم الذين
that are tackling our grandest challenges, from energy
يتعاملون مع التحديات العظيمة، من الطاقة
to environment to health care, among others,
إلى البيئة إلى الرعاية الصحية، ضمن مجالات أخرى،
and if we don't know about it and understand it,
وإذا لم نعرف كيف نعرفها و نفهمها،
then the work isn't done, and I believe it's our responsibility
عندئذ لن يكون العمل تاما، وأؤمن بأنها مسؤوليتنا
as non-scientists to have these interactions.
كغير علماء بأن نخوض مثل هذه التفاعلات.
But these great conversations can't occur if our scientists
لكن هذه النقاشات العظيمة لا يمكن أن تحدث إذا لم يدعنا
and engineers don't invite us in to see their wonderland.
علماؤنا ومهندسونا لنرى بلاد عجائبهم.
So scientists and engineers, please, talk nerdy to us.
إذاً أيها العلماء والمهندسون، رجاءً تحدثوا معنا بهوسية.
I want to share a few keys on how you can do that
أريد أن أتشارك معكم بعض المفاتيح لكيفية فعل ذلك
to make sure that we can see that your science is sexy
للتأكد من أننا نرى العلم كشيء جذاب ومثير
and that your engineering is engaging.
وأن الهندسة تدعو للانخراط فيها.
First question to answer for us: so what?
السؤال الأول لنا : ماذا إذن؟
Tell us why your science is relevant to us.
أخبرنا لماذا علومك مهمة بالنسبة بنا.
Don't just tell me that you study trabeculae,
لا تخبرني بأنك تدرس الأشعة الصغيرة،
but tell me that you study trabeculae, which is the mesh-like structure of our bones
لكن أخبرني أنك تدرس الأشعة الصغيرة، التي تبدو مثل هيكل شبكي من عظامنا
because it's important to understanding and treating osteoporosis.
لأنها مهمة لفهم وعلاج هشاشة العظام.
And when you're describing your science, beware of jargon.
وعندما تشرح تخصصك في العلوم، انتبه للمصطلحات.
Jargon is a barrier to our understanding of your ideas.
المصطلحات هي حاجز يعيق فهمنا لأفكارك.
Sure, you can say "spatial and temporal," but why not just say
بالتأكيد، يمكنك القول " مكاني وزماني،" لكن لم لا تقول فقط
"space and time," which is so much more accessible to us?
"المكان والزمان،" الذي هو مفهوم بالنسبة لنا؟
And making your ideas accessible is not the same as dumbing it down.
وجعل أفكارك مفهومة لا يماثل تسطيحها.
Instead, as Einstein said, make everything
عوضاً عن ذلك، كما قال إينشتاين، اجعل كل شيء
as simple as possible, but no simpler.
أسهل ما يمكن، لكن ليس أبسط من ذلك.
You can clearly communicate your science
يمكنك بوضوح إيصال علومك
without compromising the ideas.
بدون تخريب الأفكار.
A few things to consider are having examples, stories
قليل من الأشياء نضعها في الاعتبار مثل سرد الأمثلة و القصص
and analogies. Those are ways to engage
والمقايسات. تلك طرق لإشراكنا
and excite us about your content.
وجعلنا متحمسين لمحتوى علومك.
And when presenting your work, drop the bullet points.
وعندما تقدم عملك، أسقط النقاط الرئيسية.
Have you ever wondered why they're called bullet points? (Laughter)
هل تعجبت من قبل لم تسمى نقاط رئيسية (رصاصية)؟ (ضحك)
What do bullets do? Bullets kill,
ماذا تفعل الرصاصات؟ إنها تقتل،
and they will kill your presentation.
وستقوم بقتل عرضك التقديمي.
A slide like this is not only boring, but it relies too much
شريحة عرض مثل هذه ليست مملة فقط، لكنها تعتمد بشدة
on the language area of our brain, and causes us to become overwhelmed.
على جانب فهم اللغة في المخ، وتسبب لنا الشقاء.
Instead, this example slide by Genevieve Brown is
عوضاً، هذه الشريحة المثال من جينيفيف بروان
much more effective. It's showing that the special structure
هي أكثر فاعلية. إنها تعرض ذلك الهيكل المميز
of trabeculae are so strong that they actually inspired
للأشعة الصغيرة وهي قوية بحيث ألهمت
the unique design of the Eiffel Tower.
التصميم المتفرد لبرج إيفل.
And the trick here is to use a single, readable sentence
والخدعة هنا هي إستخدام جُملة واحدة قابلة للقراءة
that the audience can key into if they get a bit lost,
يمكن للحضور الربط معها إذا ما تاهوا عن الفهم قليلا،
and then provide visuals which appeal to our other senses
ثم توفير مادة مرئية تحرك بقية الحواس
and create a deeper sense of understanding
وتحدث تأثيرا أكثر من أجل الفهم
of what's being described.
لم يتم شرحه لهم.
So I think these are just a few keys that can help
إذاً، أعتقد أن هذه بعض المفاتيح التي تساعد
the rest of us to open that door and see the wonderland
بقيتنا لفتح ذلك الباب ورؤية بلاد العجائب
that is science and engineering.
وذلك هو العلم والهندسة.
And because the engineers that I've worked with have
ولأن المهندسين الذين عملت معهم قد
taught me to become really in touch with my inner nerd,
علموني أن أكون قريبة جداً من نفسي المهووسة بالتخصص،
I want to summarize with an equation. (Laughter)
أريد أن ألخص حديثي بمعادلة. (ضحك)
Take your science, subtract your bullet points
خذ علومك، أطرح منها النقاط الرئيسية
and your jargon, divide by relevance,
ومصطلحاتك، اقسمها على مدى ترابطها،
meaning share what's relevant to the audience,
بمعنى تقاسم ما يرتبط بالحضور،
and multiply it by the passion that you have for
واضرب ذلك بشغفك تجاه
this incredible work that you're doing,
العمل المذهل الذي تقوم به،
and that is going to equal incredible interactions
وذلك سيساوي التفاعالات المذهلة
that are full of understanding.
المليئة بالفهم.
And so, scientists and engineers, when you've solved
إذاً، أيها العلماء والمهندسون، حينما تقدمون الحل
this equation, by all means, talk nerdy to me. (Laughter)
لهذه المعادلة، بكل الطرق، تحدثوا معي بهوسية. (ضحك)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لكم. (تصفيق)